*****Huffman coding assigns variable length codewords to fixed length input characters based on their frequencies. More frequent characters are assigned shorter codewords and less frequent characters are assigned longer codewords. All edges along the path to a character contain a code digit. If they are on the left side of the tree, they will be a 0 (zero). If on the right, they'll be a 1 (one). Only the leaves will contain a letter and its frequency count. All other nodes will contain a null instead of a character, and the count of the frequency of all of it and its descendant characters.
For instance, consider the string ABRACADABRA. There are a total of 11 characters in the string. This number should match the count in the ultimately determined root of the tree. Our frequencies are A=5,B=2,R=2,C=1 and D=1. The two smallest frequencies are for C and D, both equal to 1, so we'll create a tree with them. The root node will contain the sum of the counts of its descendants, in this case 1+1=2. The left node will be the first character encountered,C, and the right will contain D. Next we have 3 items with a character count of 2: the tree we just created, the character B and the character R. The tree came first, so it will go on the left of our new root node.B will go on the right. Repeat until the tree is complete, then fill in the 1's and 0's for the edges. The finished graph looks like:

image

Input characters are only present in the leaves. Internal nodes have a character value of ϕ (NULL). We can determine that our values for characters are:

A - 0
B - 111
C - 1100
D - 1101
R - 10
Our Huffman encoded string is:

A B    R  A C     A D     A B    R  A
0 111 10 0 1100 0 1101 0 111 10 0
or
01111001100011010111100
To avoid ambiguity, Huffman encoding is a prefix free encoding technique. No codeword appears as a prefix of any other codeword.

To decode the encoded string, follow the zeros and ones to a leaf and return the character there.

You are given pointer to the root of the Huffman tree and a binary coded string to decode. You need to print the decoded string.


==>import queue as Queue

cntr = 0

class Node:
    def __init__(self, freq, data):
        self.freq = freq
        self.data = data
        self.left = None
        self.right = None
        global cntr
        self._count = cntr
        cntr = cntr + 1
        
    def __lt__(self, other):
        if self.freq != other.freq:
            return self.freq < other.freq
        return self._count < other._count

def huffman_hidden():#builds the tree and returns root
    q = Queue.PriorityQueue()

    
    for key in freq:
        q.put((freq[key], key, Node(freq[key], key) ))
    
    while q.qsize() != 1:
        a = q.get()
        b = q.get()
        obj = Node(a[0] + b[0], '\0' )
        obj.left = a[2]
        obj.right = b[2]
        q.put((obj.freq, obj.data, obj ))
        
    root = q.get()
    root = root[2]#contains root object
    return root

def dfs_hidden(obj, already):
    if(obj == None):
        return
    elif(obj.data != '\0'):
        code_hidden[obj.data] = already
        
    dfs_hidden(obj.right, already + "1")
    dfs_hidden(obj.left, already + "0")
def decodeHuff(root,s):
    ans=""
    i=0
    cur=root
    while i<len(s):
        if s[i]=="0":
            cur=cur.left
            if cur.data!='\0':
                ans+=cur.data
                cur=root
                i+=1
            else:
                i+=1
        else:
            cur=cur.right
            if cur.data!='\0':
                ans+=cur.data
                cur=root
                i+=1
            else:
                i+=1
    print(ans)
ip = input()
freq = {}#maps each character to its frequency

cntr = 0

for ch in ip:
    if(freq.get(ch) == None):
        freq[ch] = 1
    else:
        freq[ch]+=1

root = huffman_hidden()#contains root of huffman tree

code_hidden = {}#contains code for each object

dfs_hidden(root, "")

if len(code_hidden) == 1:#if there is only one character in the i/p
    for key in code_hidden:
        code_hidden[key] = "0"

toBeDecoded = ""

for ch in ip:
   toBeDecoded += code_hidden[ch]

decodeHuff(root, toBeDecoded)


LOGIC:-Check for 0's and 1's in the coded string and move to the left or right of the tree accordingly and if data in the node is not equal to "\0",print the data in the node and keep concatenating it with the further data found.